<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="http://www.inman.com" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Real Estate and Technology News for Agents, Brokers and Investors | Inman News</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com</link>
 <description>Inman News</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Growing hunger for raw land</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115533</link>
 <description>Unimproved property can be cheap, but financing poses challenges&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Steve Bergsman&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;As 2009 limped to a close, down in suburban Miami beleaguered homebuilder  Lennar Corp. sold a 9-acre parcel of raw land for $2.3 million. The property,  located in the city of Kendall,  was, according to press reports, originally acquired in 2003 for $15 million,  but I assume Lennar executives were just happy to get the property off the company&#039;s corporate books, where it sat as a non-revenue-producing asset.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The deal was notable because the market for raw land has  been relatively quiet over the past three years, despite best efforts to make  something happen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beginning around 2007, a number of investment groups began  raising capital for raw land, which had been aggressively accumulated by real estate investment trusts (REITs) and individual investors during the boom years but became toxic to corporate  accounting during the bust.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of the early strivers for raw land was Foremost  Communities LLC in Irvine, Calif., which in 2007 formed a joint venture  with Starwood Capital Group Global LLC of Greenwich, Conn., to acquire  undeveloped property.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I caught up with Steve Cameron, Foremost&#039;s CEO, at the start  of the new year and he admitted the joint venture hadn&#039;t bought any raw land  because it was instead acquiring finished lots at below replacement cost.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That&#039;s been the problem for raw land -- improved land deals  just seem more attractive. &amp;quot;I can buy a finished lot for $20,000 where the  cost of improvements were $100,000,&amp;quot; explains Cameron. &amp;quot;In essence,  I&#039;m buying the improvements at 20 cents on the dollar, paying nothing for the  land.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a recession, there seems to be a step-ladder approach to  land. First to sell are finished lots, then partially improved land, and finally,  raw land (no improvements and no entitlements).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Two years ago, H. Ross Ford, CEO and president of TCN  Worldwide in Plano, Texas, argued in print that the credit squeeze  following the subprime blow-up created opportunities for raw land  acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His thesis held that in certain hot markets like Nevada or Florida,  homebuilders had amassed large amounts of raw land for development, but with  the value of that land heading deep into a trough they needed to dispose of all  that acreage.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I asked Ford if his argument was still valid two years  later. &amp;quot;The dynamics haven&#039;t changed,&amp;quot; he replied. &amp;quot;A tremendous  amount of raw land has become devalued in the course of the economic cycle. As  such there are opportunities to buy at the bottom of the market.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Most of these opportunities have been unrealized, generally  for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; 1. If you don&#039;t have the cash, it&#039;s tough to find financing for  raw land deals. Ironically -- but logically -- in places like Florida,  Las Vegas or Southern   California where there are tremendous bargains in raw land, the  likelihood of getting financing are the slimmest.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2. For investors, a second roadblock has been a reluctance by  financial institutions to just dump assets, including raw land, into a  commercial real estate market that is already flooded with product.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The banks are in a curious position here. First, the  established financial institutions were never major lenders for raw land, so  they don&#039;t have a lot of it to dump. On the other hand, what they do have was  eased back into the market during 2009, with more to come in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the  banks weren&#039;t doing much in the way of raw land deals during the boom, their  place at the financial roulette wheel was taken by hard-money lenders, which,  as a group, have experienced high rates of mortgage failure and will need to  flush a lot of foreclosed land back through the system.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Presently, most of the deal flow is coming from existing  financial institutions and also failed banks through the Federal Deposit  Insurance Corp., observes Jason Perrin, founder and principal in Greencrossing  Real Estate Cos. in Aliso Viejo, Calif. &amp;quot;Deal flow picked up in the latter  part of 2009 and we are going to see more raw stuff come through the pipeline  in 2010.&amp;quot;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are a couple of key points to consider when investing in raw  land.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First of all, prices are -- pardon the pun -- all over the  place, because in many badly hit regions, raw land in a technical sense has no  value other than speculation. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, in 2005, a home in a partially completed  development sold for $500,000 with $100,000 of that covering the cost of the  land. Now that house is worth $350,000, with the $150,000 decline attributed to the  land, giving it a value of minus $50,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No one is going to give the rest of the  land in the development away, so a buyer might offer $5,000 for the land and  the seller responds by saying, &amp;quot;I will (or will not) sell at that  price.&amp;quot; Let the negotiations begin.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Secondly, investing in raw land often means a lengthy hold  period. Raw land Rule No. 1 says: the further the distance from the center of  business and residential activity, the longer the hold.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Rule No. 2 maintains: the further out,  the less maintenance. Closer in, community regulations can demand a certain  level of standards for the property. Taxes will have to be paid during the hold  period, but in some locales if the land is used for grazing or agriculture, tax  breaks can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stronger markets recover first so many investors will only  buy in A and B locations. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jurisdictions are also important because some cities make it  easy to get entitlements and other cities do not. Although, as Perrin points  out, now is a great time to process entitlements. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;These are tough times, and counties and cities are  happy to get from developers any sort of extraction,&amp;quot; he says.  &amp;quot;Developers have more leverage right now to emerge ... with entitlements and at less cost.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;One theory about raw land holds that bigger is better  because the cost entitling 2,000 acres is probably not much different than  entitling 200 acres. Nevertheless, smaller investors shouldn&#039;t despair.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ford gives this example: A friend bought 18 acres of raw  land outside of Dallas  10 years ago. He paid $14,000 an acre. He was recently offered $50,000 an acre  for it and turned it down.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Nothing precludes you from buying 10 acres well beyond  the current growth parameters of your city and holding onto it until the time  comes to sell sometime in the future,&amp;quot; Ford said.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steve Bergsman is  a freelance writer in Arizona and author of several books, including&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-0470405279.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;After the Fall:  Opportunities and Strategies for Real Estate Investing in the Coming Decade&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Unimproved property can be cheap, but financing poses challenges</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Steve Bergsman</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115533</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Tips on remodeling to sell</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115574</link>
 <description>Sellers hit snag with kitchen paint, drawer choices&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Paul Bianchina&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: We are planning to  sell our home next year. We tried the easiest route to brighten up the kitchen:  painting the dark wood cabinets a lighter color, as we have a faux wood  laminate countertop. We went with a two-toned effect, with the cabinets done in  white and the doors and drawers done in a semigloss beige. It does not look all  that great and the doors stick: What would you suggest? &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Also, the drawers are  an odd rail system with a wheel on an arm at the back of the drawer that hooks into  the rail above the drawer -- they always come off and stick horribly. Any  advice would be wonderful and highly appreciated, as we are on a very tight  budget.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: When remodeling to sell, always stick with colors and  materials that are as universally appealing as possible. In the kitchen, I  would go with all white on the cabinets, since the two-tone look is not  something that will appeal to most people. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&#039;s hard to say why the cabinet doors stick. If they didn&#039;t  stick before the paint job, my suspicion would be that you got paint on the  hinges, or you built up too much paint in the area of the hinges that is  binding the door, or you closed and/or reinstalled the doors before the paint  was completely dry. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you are going to repaint the doors, I would suggest  sanding them down to bare wood before you repaint -- putting another coat on at  this point is probably asking for trouble. I would also replace the hinges.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The old-style drawer slides you mention have always been a  problem. I&#039;m not sure those things worked right even when they were brand new!  I would start by removing each drawer, then checking to be sure that the wheel,  track and other components are well secured.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They were often held in place by a  staple or a single screw, so they work loose and drop out of alignment quite  easily. Install more screws as needed to keep them in place. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over time, the plastic front wheels wear out as well, which  also messes with the alignment and operation. You can order new wheels and also  complete replacement slides from Rockler Woodworking and Hardware at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockler.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rockler.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally, make sure you clean everything thoroughly with a  degreaser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: (We have problems) with  our contractor not doing his job; can we fire him and hire someone who will do  the job? He is threatening to sue us. We contracted him to do the work, but  there have been many problems and there is not a written contact.&lt;/i&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: You say that you contracted with him, but later you say  you have no written contract. Not having a written contract can make things  considerably messier. You apparently have no written specifications, no start  and completion dates, no agreed-upon price, nothing. Instead you have some type  of oral contract, which makes it very difficult to determine whether a breach  has occurred, and if so, by whom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of that is what affects your question  about whether or not you can fire him. With no written record for the courts to  fall back on, it becomes a matter of who said what to whom -- in other words,  it&#039;s going to be your word against his. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here are my suggestions:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sit down with the contractor and discuss the problems. See  if you can reach a compromise of some sort. It is very much in everyone&#039;s best  interests to calm down, take a deep breath and try to work something out. He  may want out of this job just as much as you want him gone.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If that doesn&#039;t work, then consult with an attorney to see  what your exact legal status is, especially since he&#039;s threatened a lawsuit  (although my gut feeling is that this is just a scare tactic). Since a licensed  contractor is forbidden in most states from doing work without a written  contract, the person you hired may have a problem on his hands as well, so you  will also want to clarify that.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Please learn from this mistake. In the future, never  undertake construction work of any kind without a written contract.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: I am installing an  electric oven/microwave combo into my new cherry cabinet. The oven instructions  suggest to slide it in and screw in the mount brackets. My question is: The  oven weighs 230 pounds and I do not see the &amp;quot;face&amp;quot; of the cabinet  supporting the entire oven, (no bottom support). Now, the oven manufacturer  also recommends at least 4 inches from the bottom of the oven to the bottom of  cabinet -- thus not being able to put a shelf in for support. What do you  recommend?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: Typically, what the oven manufacturer is referring to is  clearance between the bottom of the oven door and anything below it, such as  the top of a drawer. However, the oven manufacturers understand that the oven  needs a lot more support than just the cabinet face frame, and there will be a  specific set of instructions packaged with the oven that shows where the supports  should go. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I have seen over the years is either a plywood bottom  in the cabinet that the oven slides directly onto, or a plywood panel with  &amp;quot;2-by&amp;quot; lumber pieces on top that are installed in a particular spot  so that they support the oven&#039;s feet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the oven is typically  screwed to the face or inside edge of the face frame (or both) to provide  additional resistance against tipping when the oven door is opened. With cherry  or any hardwood, be sure you predrill the cabinets.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Remodeling and repair  questions? E-mail Paul at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:paulbianchina@inman.com&quot;&gt;paulbianchina@inman.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Sellers hit snag with kitchen paint, drawer choices</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 10 07:23:03 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Paul Bianchina</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115574</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The house that got away</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115581</link>
 <description>Home Sale Hindsight&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: My wife and I were  house hunting for months, and finally found a place we liked. Amazingly, since  we had been outbid so many times before, we were able to get into contract on  it. We had all the normal inspections in our area -- termite, home inspection  and a roof inspection -- and they did find some things that needed to be worked  on, but there were also some really great upgrades and improvements that  checked out OK. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Right before we were  going to remove our inspection contingency, I asked my friend, who is a  contractor, to come out and inspect the house, too. He didn&#039;t even walk inside --  he said he didn&#039;t like the way some of the things he could see on the home&#039;s  exterior were done, and that the inside work was probably &amp;quot;no good&amp;quot;  either.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;He said he wouldn&#039;t pay anymore than $200,000 for it -- and we were in  contract at over $250,000! I immediately called our real estate agent and  canceled the purchase. Now, months later, we  still have no house, and we can see the tax credit about to pass us by. I still  think about that house all the time and wonder if it was the one that got away.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: Well, the fact that the tax credit deadline is looming is  really of no significance, except that it might have been the spark to your  regret. It&#039;s a great incentive to be out looking, but certainly not enough to  warrant buying a home you wouldn&#039;t otherwise.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have worked first-hand with more than one set of clients  through fact patterns extremely similar to yours. So, I have lots of thoughts  about how you can meaningfully reflect on, analyze and gain lessons from your  experience. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My first observation derives from a rule of mine: If your contractor  friend is your ultimate decision-maker, then he should have seen the place  before you wrote an offer on it. Now, it might sound extreme to your ears to  hear me call him your &amp;quot;ultimate decision-maker,&amp;quot; but think about it --  that is precisely the power and position you put your contractor friend in. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You said the home had passed the muster of you, your wife  and at least three inspectors (who, by the way, make a living advising  homebuyers on property condition for the precise purpose of informing their  decision whether to buy), but that your friend&#039;s word -- without even entering  the home -- was enough to make you cancel the deal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;From this -- the fact that your friend was your ultimate  decision-maker -- I derive two lessons for you, and pieces of advice going  forward. If he&#039;s going to be your ultimate decision-maker, he should be seeing  properties with you or, at the very latest, before you write an offer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In every  event, he should be the first to see a place before you spend money on  professional inspectors. OK, that was the first piece of advice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The second piece is that I recommend you spend some time  deciding whether you are comfortable with him making your decision for you. If  so, fabulous. If that makes you at all uncomfortable, though, I would like to  offer you some thoughts.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First off, your friend -- who is undoubtedly a fabulous  contractor -- is likely not an authoritative source on home values in your  area, the real estate market, or even on the average condition of homes for  sale in your area. He doesn&#039;t advise real estate consumers and sell homes  everyday, so as to have a good understanding of local list-price-to-sale-price  ratios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He probably doesn&#039;t appreciate what it actually costs to buy a home  like that on today&#039;s market, or whether/how much &amp;quot;your&amp;quot; home was  discounted for its condition problems.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unless you simply have the sort of relationship where you  are comfortable allowing your friend to exercise enormous power in your life  decisions, what your friend is an authority on is fairly limited. He might be  an authority on the work that is needed, and he is definitely an authority on  what he would charge you (notice I didn&#039;t say what it would cost, because it&#039;s  difficult for him to know what other contractors would charge you) to do  various work to the property. So, that&#039;s what I would take advice from him on,  going forward.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Licensed and/or (in states where licensing is not available)  certified home inspectors have a special expertise (different from that of a  contractor, although many inspectors are contractors, by training) in looking  at a property with a very thorough eye toward the long laundry list of items  that should or do factor into a reasonable buyer&#039;s decision-making -- the  things about a home someone should understand before making a decision whether  or not to buy it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Also, in some states, California  included, your general home inspector cannot also be in the business of home  improvement contracting -- this rule is designed to eliminate any monetary  incentive for the inspector to inflate the list of &amp;quot;work needed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, when I encourage you to rely on a mixture of information  for making your decision whether to buy any given property, taking your  friend&#039;s feedback into account, but also that of your broker or agent (who, I  can promise you, doesn&#039;t want you to buy a home that you regret buying later,  if that&#039;s an avoidable outcome) and your professional inspectors, I&#039;m  encouraging you to assign appropriate weight to each stream of input, given the  expertise and seriousness of the giver. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, the fact that your friend stated what he  wouldn&#039;t pay, after refusing to even come in and deeming improvements &amp;quot;no  good,&amp;quot; sight unseen, leads me to suspect he might not have been treating  your request for his input with the gravity it deserves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you still want him to be your deal-maker/deal-breaker,  moving forward, get his (free) opinion first, but only after asking him to  treat your request seriously, professionally and thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson is author of &amp;quot;The  Savvy Woman&#039;s Homebuying Handbook&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Trillion Dollar Women: Use  Your Power to Make Buying and Remodeling Decisions.&amp;quot; Ask her a real estate  question online or visit her Web site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rethinkrealestate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rethinkrealestate.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Home Sale Hindsight</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 10 08:40:18 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tara-Nicholle Nelson</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115581</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Golden Years, in reverse</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115450</link>
 <description>Traveling retirees&#039; home serves as financial cushion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tom Kelly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;What many people have now -- house, lifestyle, neighborhood,  friends, church, clubs -- is exactly what they&#039;d like to keep.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, many older folks simply don&#039;t know how or  where to look to find the funds that would allow them to maintain the status  quo. The immediate need for seniors now is supplementing the income to provide  the standard of living they desire.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the past, the typical reverse mortgage was taken out by a  single woman, 75, who needed funds to fix up her home so she could  comfortably age in place. Reverse mortgages now are also being used to support  a more well-to-do routine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, Frank Williams, 77, and his wife, Carla, own 35  weeks of timeshares each year in five different timeshare systems. They work  points, bonus time and favored status like some people work airline miles. They  know how to successfully maneuver through each different organization to gain  the maximum overall benefit. They are actively filling in their timeshare schedule  into calendar year 2022. Now that&#039;s organization!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Williamses took out a reverse mortgage on their  principal residence in New Mexico  not to buy more timeshare weeks, but to make sure they didn&#039;t have to skimp  getting to them, or cut back on activities once they arrived.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I know a lot of people are skeptical about reverse  mortgages, but it worked for us,&amp;quot; Frank said. &amp;quot;Our friends want to  leave everything they have to their kids, and that&#039;s OK. But we&#039;re not primed  to punish our kids by spending all of our money. Our kids are doing fine --  they own their own homes, and would rather see us enjoy the rest of our  lives.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consumers can choose how to receive the money from a reverse  mortgage. The options include a lump sum, fixed monthly payments (for life), a  line of credit, or a combination of the above. The most popular option, chosen  by more than 60 percent of borrowers, is the line of credit, which allows  consumers to draw on the loan proceeds at any time. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The size of the reverse mortgage depends on age at  application, the loan type and home value. In general, the older the consumer  and the more valuable the home (and the less amount owed), the larger the  reverse mortgage. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A reverse mortgage can be viewed similar to a home equity  loan but without a monthly payment. Owners do not repay the loan as long as the  home remains the principal residence. Income and credit rating are not  considered when qualifying for the loan. There is no requirement that owners requalify  during the term of the reverse mortgage, yet property taxes and home insurance  must remain current.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With a home equity loan, borrowers must make regular  payments to repay the loan. These payments begin as soon as the loan is  originated. To qualify for such a loan, the borrower must earn a monthly income  great enough to make those payments. If payments are not made, the lender can  foreclose, forcing the sale of the home. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Williamses took out a home equity loan to do a major  remodel on their home. Frank repaid most of the debt by selling some lackluster  bonds and then paid off the remainder with a reverse mortgage from Golden  Gateway Financial. The couple also receives $1,500 a month, tax-free, for the  next 20 years from funds remaining in the reverse mortgage.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I had some assets that I didn&#039;t really want to sell  because I thought they would rebound and do quite well,&amp;quot; Frank said. &amp;quot;So,  I look at the reverse mortgage as a way of buying us some time for those assets  to come back. The bonds that I did sell were not yielding anything close to the  interest rate we were paying on the home equity loan, so I sold them and paid  it down.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In winter, the Williamses spend up to five consecutive weeks  in the same timeshare unit on the Big Island of Hawaii. They then will hop over  to Kauai for a couple of weeks and then maybe hit Palm   Springs and San Diego in California before  drifting back home to New Mexico.  Northern Idaho is a favorite summer spotfor the couple.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But why would they want to pay $22,000-$23,000 in annual timeshare  fees rather than simply plunk that down on a mortgage for a second home?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I have no delusions about timesharing being a good  investment. They&#039;re a lousy investment,&amp;quot; Frank said. &amp;quot;But we enjoy  doing what we do, going where we go. We have no regrets and wouldn&#039;t change anything.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tom Kelly&#039;s book  &amp;quot;Cashing In on a Second Home in Mexico: How to Buy, Rent and Profit  from Property South of the Border&amp;quot; was written with Mitch Creekmore,  senior vice president of Houston-based Stewart International. The book is  available in retail stores, on Amazon.com and on tomkelly.com.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tom Kelly&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Traveling retirees&#039; home serves as financial cushion</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tom Kelly</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tom Kelly&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115450</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Negotiate finder&#039;s fee in soft market</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115506</link>
 <description>Rent it Right&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Janet Portman&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: My wife and I are  looking for an apartment in a cool area of town, and fortunately there&#039;s a lot  to choose from. Many of the listings are handled by apartment-finding companies.  Some of them charge the tenants if they find a rental through the company, and  some of them say it&#039;s free -- that the landlord pays the rental fee. Should we  avoid the ones that will charge us? Why should we pay when there are many  listings that we can rent without the fee? --Joe and Alisha F.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: In a soft market, as you describe, it&#039;s unusual for  apartment-finding agencies to ask tenants to pay the fee if they find a rental  through the agency. Most landlords who use these services understand the  workings of the market, and know that the pool of applicants will be smaller if  the prospect has to tack on a finder&#039;s fee to the regular costs of renting an  apartment. As you say, it makes no sense to pay a fee when there are plenty of  places you could rent without one.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But before you categorically scratch off every listing that  requires the tenant to pay a fee, consider a few things. First, is the rent set  right at market rates? Landlords who are competing for scarce tenants might set  the rent a bit below market, hoping to attract a larger pool of applicants, but  make up the difference by charging a fee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By spreading the finder&#039;s fee across,  say, 12 months on a lease, and adding that money to the monthly rent, the  landlord ends up with a fair market rent. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you&#039;re dealing with a landlord who is following this  plan, it would be a mistake to conclude either that the rental is a real steal  or that the landlord is trying to rip off prospective tenants. Instead, you  should do just what the landlord has done: Add the fee to the stated rent for  the term of the rental to figure out the real price of renting the unit. It may  still be a good deal, despite the fee and the soft market.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now suppose the rent is already at market rates, and you&#039;re  still being asked to pay a finder&#039;s fee. If you really want that particular  rental, there&#039;s no law against asking the agency to lower the fee. If they know  you are an interested -- and qualified -- tenant, they would be foolish to lose  you and risk another rent-less month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make your case, find out how long the  unit has been empty. Ask if you can talk directly to the owner. Don&#039;t be afraid  to flex your market muscle: You can be sure that when the market is hot,  landlords will do the same and expect renters to foot the bill.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: I lost out on a  rental because the landlord told me that the screening report he got listed an  eviction. That&#039;s simply not true -- I&#039;ve never had an eviction lawsuit filed  against me. What can I do to make sure the report is accurate? I faxed my  complaint to the screening company, but they said I&#039;d have to send in a written  complaint on their form (which they have not sent). --Jay B.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: Errors in credit and screening reports are all too common  these days. Collectors of credit information, striving to gather ever more  information at faster speeds, make mistakes. And ironically, as the desire to  prevent identity theft grows, the people furnishing credit and other  information to the agencies are less and less willing to provide a person&#039;s  unique, identifying information (such as date of birth and Social Security  number).  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These providers, including landlords, are afraid of putting  individual information into reports that may be accessed by those who have no  legitimate reason to see them. The result is much more confusion, as those with  the same or similar names are mistaken for each other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Federal law, however, gives consumers a way to fight back  when erroneous information pops up in a credit report or screening report  (screening agencies are subject to the same rules as credit agencies).  According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ftc.gov/os/statutes/031224fcra.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sections  609(a)(1) and 610(a) of the Fair Credit Reporting Act&lt;/a&gt;, consumers may demand, in  writing, that the agency investigate the alleged error, and do so promptly  (usually within 30 days).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&#039;s no requirement that the demand be by mail  rather than fax, let alone that it be done on the screening agency&#039;s form.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In fact, one of the largest tenant screening agencies,  FirstAdvantage SafeRent Inc., was recently fined for doing just what you  describe. After the U.S. Federal Trade Commission filed a lawsuit in  federal court, alleging that SafeRent rejected faxed reinvestigation requests,  SafeRent settled (for a paltry $100,000), and promised never to do it again. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Readers may recognize this company as the same one that, a  few years ago, was the target of a class-action lawsuit in New York charging that the company failed to note on its reports how an eviction filing turned out. Tenants who won the evictions --  even those whose landlords dismissed the eviction lawsuits -- allegedly got screening  reports that said, very confusingly, &amp;quot;Eviction, case filed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This  notation, with a comma that suggests that the eviction in fact happened, was a  virtual blacklisting, because many landlords would assume that the tenant was  at fault. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;SafeRent also agreed to make its database more complete and  up-to-date, and to implement procedures to review and, if appropriate and  reasonable, address any potential problems that may arise. It looks like they  needed to be reminded of their promise.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Your next step should be to write to the screening agency  and tell them about the error. Also contact the landlord who supposedly  furnished this error. Check out the FTC&#039;s tips for consumers on how to contest  erroneous information in a credit or screening report, &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ftc.gov/bcp/edu/pubs/consumer/credit/cre21.shtm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to  Dispute Credit Report Errors&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;quot;  which includes a sample letter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Janet Portman is an attorney and managing  editor at Nolo. She specializes in landlord/tenant law and is co-author of &amp;quot;Every  Landlord&#039;s Legal Guide&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Every Tenant&#039;s Legal Guide.&amp;quot; She  can be reached at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:janet@inman.com&quot;&gt;janet@inman.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Janet Portman&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Rent it Right</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 10 07:15:31 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Janet Portman</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Janet Portman&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115506</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>High offer can botch short sale</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115507</link>
 <description>REThink Real Estate&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: I&#039;m in the process  of trying to buy a home. I made an offer on  a home that was a short sale and,  because there were several other  offers and I really liked the place, my offer  was above the asking  price. The listing agent said I was the highest bidder. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Then, we got a  counteroffer from the seller and it was actually  for a price lower than the  price I&#039;d originally offered! Then, my agent  suggested that I make a counteroffer  back higher than the seller&#039;s  counteroffer but lower than my original offer  price. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I am totally lost here  -- I don&#039;t understand what the seller&#039;s  strategy is or what I should do next.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A: The universe of short sales does boggle the mind! And  from the buyer&#039;s perspective, it&#039;s more than a little crazy-making, because so  much of what impacts whether or not the short sale will be approved by the  seller&#039;s bank(s) (so that you can have your house!) is totally and completely  out of your and your agent&#039;s control. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Other than your offer price, you have very little or no  ability to impact the bank&#039;s evaluation of the transaction. Rather, the  seller&#039;s financials and how they and the offer are presented to and managed by  the listing agent are much more critical to the eventual outcome of your short-sale  transaction.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Accordingly, one of the factors I look at before showing a  short-sale listing to my own buyer clients is the listing agent&#039;s track record  of successfully closing short sales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And interestingly enough, it tends to be  the listing agents who have done the most short sales that come up with these  deceptively wise strategies, because they&#039;ve learned the hard way what does and  doesn&#039;t work, and want to maximize the chances that their hard work will  culminate in an approved short sale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Don&#039;t hesitate to ask your agent to ask the listing agent  what their thought process and strategies are behind a seemingly bizarre  counteroffer or anything else. If they can be reached by phone or e-mail, often  they&#039;ll illuminate you so that you don&#039;t have to feel like you&#039;re just taking  shots in the dark with no rhyme or reason.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Need-to-Knows&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&#039;m not sure how much you know about short sales, so I&#039;ll  start from the basics: Short sales take a long time. I still hear buyers call  them &amp;quot;quick sales,&amp;quot; and constantly find myself correcting that extreme  misconception. Where an &amp;quot;ordinary&amp;quot; sale is taking around 30-45 days  on today&#039;s market, it is very common for short sales to take four to six months  (or even much longer than that) to close.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A year is not unheard of. The  &amp;quot;short&amp;quot; refers to the fact that the purchase price is less than -- or  &amp;quot;short&amp;quot; of -- the amount of the seller&#039;s required payoff to their  lender(s). As a result, the seller&#039;s lender(s) must approve of all the terms of  the transaction before it can close. And sometimes they do, sometimes they  don&#039;t. If any lender doesn&#039;t approve of the transaction, the deal will not  close.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With that basic understanding in place, you&#039;ll see why  short-sale listing agents are very cognizant of the fact that the buyer they  get into contract with is not the buyer they may close the deal with. Because  short sales take so long and are so uncertain to close, buyers often continue  house hunting while they are in contract to buy a short-sale property.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many  will cancel their short-sale contract if they find another place they like more  or have a higher certainty of being able to actually buy.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, when you walk in and make a really high offer to buy a  short-sale property, the listing agent is often very wary of taking that offer. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here&#039;s what they fear: Say, hypothetically, that they accept  your offer and submit the contract for approval to the bank(s). One bank  approves the terms. The other bank is still considering it. In the meantime,  you go off and find another place and back out of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now the seller is  stuck unable to sell the place at any less than your astronomically high offer  price, because the bank has already approved it at that price, and may now believe  that any price lower than that is below fair market value and an unacceptable  loss for them to take. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Listing agents who have done many short sales have almost  always had one experience like this, and know that it might actually be a  disservice to their clients to put a super-high offer into contract. It can be  the thing that prohibits their seller from being able to sell their home, in  the final analysis.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You don&#039;t mention if the seller issued multiple  counteroffers, but I wouldn&#039;t be surprised if the seller did, in an effort to get  backup offers lined up in case you bail before the deal closes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the seller did issue multiple counteroffers,  it&#039;s not unusual for the counteroffers to bring the lower-priced offers up some  and bring the higher-priced offers down a bit, so the seller can have several  people lined up who are all willing to pay a fair, but not outrageous, price  for the place. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&#039;ve also seen short sellers counter back a lower price  anticipating that they might need to later request a price increase or cash  contribution from the buyer in order to get the banks to accept the offer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Action Plan&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What you do from here is really situation-specific. Make  sure that your agent has spoken with the listing agent to get a peek at the listing agent&#039;s and the seller&#039;s thought processes before you respond to their counteroffer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some listing agents do expect that you&#039;ll offer slightly more than they  countered; others might just want you to accept it, but be aware that you might  have to pay more if and when the bank(s) require it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Either way, don&#039;t get your heart set on a short sale -- ever -- until every bank involved has approved the deal, and your inspection,  appraisal and loan underwriting are complete. And don&#039;t stop looking. Good  luck!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson is author of &amp;quot;The  Savvy Woman&#039;s Homebuying Handbook&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Trillion Dollar Women: Use Your  Power to Make Buying and Remodeling Decisions.&amp;quot; Ask her a real estate  question online or visit her Web site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rethinkrealestate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rethinkrealestate.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>REThink Real Estate</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 10 07:27:13 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tara-Nicholle Nelson</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115507</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Beware when buying &#039;as is&#039;</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115378</link>
 <description>The $20,000 mistake&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Barry Stone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;DEAR BARRY: Before we  purchased our home, the sellers hired their own home inspector. We were given a  copy of the report and bought the house &amp;quot;as is&amp;quot; because no major  problems were disclosed. Two months later, we had a sewage backup. We snaked it  out, but two weeks later it happened again, and then again, and then again … Our  plumber says the main sewer line has major root damage. A new line is needed,  and the repair bid is $5,000. That&#039;s problem No. 1. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Problem No. 2 is the  large deck and retaining wall in the backyard. The structure is totally rotted,  and replacement is estimated at $15,000. Shouldn&#039;t these problems have been  disclosed by the sellers and their home inspector? --Michael&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;DEAR MICHAEL: Some disclosures should have come from the  sellers, and some from the home inspector. So let&#039;s sort through the details.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A home inspector cannot know about internal problems in a  sewer line. All an inspector can do is report defects that are apparent at the  time of the inspection. If a sewage backup occurs every few weeks or months but  is not occurring at the time of the home inspection, the inspector has no way  of knowing it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Liability in this case points toward the seller. If sewage backups  happen repeatedly, the seller was probably aware of it and should have  disclosed it. Unfortunately, prior knowledge by the seller is not easily  proven. Sometimes you can learn details of past problems by asking the  neighbors. Sometimes the neighbors can recall which plumbing company visited  the property. It&#039;s all a matter of detective work, which may or may not lead to  proof.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then we have the deck problem. Rotted wood in decks and  retaining walls is usually reported by a pest control operator, commonly known  as a termite inspector. But wood rot can also be found by home inspectors who  take the time to investigate. If the underside of the deck is accessible for  inspection, that definitely helps, but a badly rotted deck usually has apparent  damage on exposed wood members.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A major mistake in your transaction was trusting the seller&#039;s  inspection report, without hiring a home inspector of your own. Regardless of  the qualifications of the seller&#039;s inspector, it is always best to have someone  conduct an inspection specifically on your behalf, assuming that you hire a  highly experienced inspector. This should have been recommended by your agent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At this point, the sewer problem needs to be diagnosed and  corrected, once and for all, rather than paying for repeated snaking of the  line. Begin by finding a plumbing company that does video inspections of sewer  lines. Then the problem can be determined with certainty. If a new line to the  street is needed, inquire about installing a synthetic lining in the existing  line, rather than excavating the yard and installing a new pipe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As for the deck and retaining wall, the home inspector  should return to the property for a second look and explain why the damage was  not disclosed in the inspection report.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To write to Barry  Stone, please visit him on the Web at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.housedetective.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.housedetective.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Barry Stone&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>The $20,000 mistake</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Barry Stone</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Barry Stone&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115378</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Drunk on alphabet soup</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115413</link>
 <description>Agent designations, certifications explained&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Mary Umberger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like a sea of medals on a general&#039;s chest, many real estate  agents&#039; business cards are festooned with initials after their names.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Agents may boast about such designations or certifications  as ABR, SRES, GRI or a host of others intended to be a testament to expertise  they bring to a home-sale transaction. However, there are so many of them that  they may be alphabet soup to the average consumer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The acronyms usually represent coursework focused on a  single aspect of real estate, such as transactions involving raw land,  foreclosures or international properties, explained Colleen Ryan, manager of  education services for the National Association of Realtors. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Or, she said, they may indicate broader specialized  coursework in residential transactions (as opposed to commercial real estate,  for example) or working specifically with homebuyers (as opposed to sellers). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Adding to the potential confusion, within NAR there&#039;s a  difference between a certification and a designation. &amp;quot;Designations have  additional requirements that need to be met, in addition to the  coursework,&amp;quot; Ryan said. &amp;quot;The coursework is also more detailed and  longer in terms of the number of hours that must be completed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Designations also have a dues/membership fee attached  that must be renewed to keep their membership current,&amp;quot; she explained.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The NAR offers courses leading to nearly two dozen such  designations and certifications, though many of them deal with such interests  as appraisal or brokerage management, rather areas that directly touch on  consumer issues.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And though NAR-sponsored courses dominate the acronyms,  other real estate organizations also bestow certification in such things as  green building and home staging.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The courses vary widely in their requirements, from an  afternoon to several days; many of them are offered online now, an option  that&#039;s particularly popular with younger agents, Ryan said.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whether these accolades necessarily benefit consumers is  something that even agents themselves argue about -- sometimes hotly -- given  the broad disparity in the depth of the courses and whether coursework actually  translates into experience. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;(The Realtors suggest, at least, that the completed courses  translate into earnings. The trade group cites a 2009 survey that says the  median income of agents without designations was about half that of agents with  at least one designation.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, consumers who have little background in the  world of real estate agents probably couldn&#039;t parse a CIPS from an RSPS. A  quick guide to some of the letters they might encounter in the Acronym Jungle:  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;SFR&lt;/b&gt; (Short  Sales and Foreclosure Resource). The new course, leading to a certification, is  a sign of our times, Ryan said. It&#039;s intended to teach agents how to navigate  the byzantine path through foreclosures and short sales, in which seller and  his lender agree to sell a home for an amount less than the value of the  mortgage.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;ABR&lt;/b&gt; (Accredited  Buyer Representative). The designation course covers legal considerations and  duties specific to working with buyers, negotiation skills, and other topics.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;CRS&lt;/b&gt; (Certified  Residential Specialist). The designation requires that an agent complete a  specified number of transactions and includes several courses in such topics as  effective sales presentations or real estate technology. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;GRI&lt;/b&gt; (Graduate  Realtor Institute). The designation course requires 90 to 95 hours of  coursework on contract law, taxes, finance and other topics.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;SRES&lt;/b&gt; (Senior  Real Estate Specialist). The designation course is intended to develop skills  specific to the needs of buyers and sellers aged 55 and over. It includes  materials on tax laws, probate and estate planning.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;RSPS&lt;/b&gt; (Resort  &amp;amp; Second-Home Property Specialist). As the name implies, the certification  course teaches the essentials of buying, selling, or managing resort properties  or second homes. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;ABR&lt;/b&gt; (Accredited  Buyer&#039;s Representative). After the two-day designation course, agents have three  years to verify five completed transactions in which they acted solely as a  legally designated buyer&#039;s agent. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;quot;Green&amp;quot;  designations&lt;/b&gt; -- Real estate agents can establish environmental-awareness  credentials in a couple of ways. EcoBroker is a designation from an organization unaffiliated  with NAR. Agents can earn the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecobroker.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EcoBroker designation&lt;/a&gt; by completing an assortment  of two-day courses, in class or online, on such concerns as radon, asbestos,  indoor air quality, LEED certification, solar power, etc. NAR offers a GREEN designation, on similar topics.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;CRP&lt;/b&gt; (Certified Relocation Professional). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldwideerc.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Worldwide  ERP&lt;/a&gt;, a trade group for the relocation industry, offers an exam for agents and  others in the business on corporate relocation policy, appraising, residential  real estate, tax and legal issues, among other topics. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mary Umberger is a  freelance writer in Chicago.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Agent designations, certifications explained</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Mary Umberger</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 &lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115413</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Gas main, where art thou?</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115444</link>
 <description>In case of leak, shutoff is imperative&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Bill and Kevin  Burnett&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Q: I live in San Francisco and I have  old gas lines that are still very, very live. How can I locate the main line  coming from the street? The blueprints for this building are long gone, since  City Hall and most of the city burned down after the 1906 earthquake and fire.  Is there any way of locating it?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A: The blueprints in the old City Hall wouldn&#039;t help in  locating gas lines, even if they had not gone up in smoke in 1906.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The regional utility company, PG&amp;amp;E, has the most  up-to-date information about gas mains and services. As we&#039;ve mentioned before,  Kevin spent three summers repairing and replacing gas lines for a section of Oakland&#039;s PG&amp;amp;E  division in the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beginning in the 1970s, and extending to the present  day, PG&amp;amp;E has been systematically replacing antiquated gas lines. The  useful life of iron pipes was about 50 years -- after that, they began to rust  through and leak.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To compound the failure rate, the oldest pipes were joined  with lead/oakum bell joints rather than welded together. Earth movement  stressed these joints, creating leaks. There was many a day Kevin stood with  his head down in a hole, re-leading these joints with a caulking tool and  hammer and fitting them with a repair clamp made of rubber and iron.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We give this brief history lesson to point out that the gas  main serving your home is probably not the 1906 version. It has probably been  replaced at least twice during the last century. The main and service line are  probably plastic, with the exception of a small section of iron pipe that comes  out of the ground.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Locating the line coming into the house is simple. First,  find your gas meter. On one side of the meter is a regulator. The regulator is  a saucer-like device that looks a little like the Starship Enterprise (from &amp;quot;Star Trek&amp;quot;) laid on  its end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its purpose is to reduce the pressure of natural gas traveling from  the main before it goes through the gas meter and enters the house lines.  Pressure in the mains runs at 15 pounds per square inch and up -- enough to  create regular leaks in gas appliances.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The pipe going into the regulator is the main line coming  from the street. Between the regulator and the point where the pipe exits the  ground or enters the house you&#039;ll notice a valve. This is the shutoff valve for  the house. On the side of the valve is a horizontal bar. When the rectangular  bar on the valve runs parallel to the pipe, the gas is on. When the rectangular  bar is perpendicular to the pipe, the valve is off.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We recommend that you keep a 14-inch crescent wrench or a  special gas-valve wrench near the meter, so that in case of an unexpected gas  leak the valve can be turned off.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If it is necessary to turn the gas off, consider having a  PG&amp;amp;E service worker come to the house and relight any pilot lights and  verify that your gas appliances are operating properly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Bill and Kevin Burnett&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>In case of leak, shutoff is imperative</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 10 08:55:39 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Bill and Kevin  Burnett</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Bill and Kevin Burnett&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115444</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Who pays for contractor&#039;s cost miscue?</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115454</link>
 <description>Law of the Land&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the case &lt;a href=&quot;http://coa.courts.mi.gov/documents/OPINIONS/FINAL/COA/20100204_C288439_32_288439.OPN.PDF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ProBuild  LLC v. Ellis&lt;/a&gt;, homeowners Ronald and Kimberly Jinks entered into a contract  with home improvement contractor Steven Ellis for work to the Jinkses&#039; home.  The Jinkses paid slightly more than the contract price, which included labor  and materials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the contract and the work was completed, supplier ProBuild  North LLC (ProBuild) filed a mechanic&#039;s lien against the Jinkses home in an  effort to recover the amount of Ellis&#039; outstanding bill for building materials  that Ellis used on the Jinkses&#039; job. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eventually, ProBuild sought to foreclose on the lien,  collecting against the Michigan Department of Labor and Economic Growth&#039;s  Homeowner Construction Lien Recovery Fund, which then sought to be  repaid by the Jinkses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The trial court found that because the Jinkses had paid Ellis  the full contract price for the project, they were not liable to ProBuild for  the unpaid supplies. The fund appealed the trial court&#039;s ruling.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Michigan Court of Appeals upheld the trial court&#039;s  ruling. ProBuild and the fund argued that Ellis&#039; quote -- and the resulting  contract with the Jinkses -- charged the Jinkses less than the value of the  improvements they received. On appeal, ProBuild and the fund argued that the  Jinkses should be required to compensate them for the value the Jinkses  received above and beyond the contract amount.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, the version of Michigan Construction Lien Act  Section 570.1203 applicable at the time of the underlying events expressly  provided that homeowners could not be liable under a construction lien where  the owners filed an affidavit with the court stating they had: &amp;quot;(a) paid  the contractor for the improvement to the residential structure and the amount  of the payment; (b) not colluded with any person to obtain a payment from the  fund; and (c) cooperated and will continue to cooperate with the department in  the defense of the fund.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ronald Jinks had filed such an affidavit with the trial  court, and the trial court had found that it was materially undisputed that the  Jinkses had actually paid Ellis more than the contract amount.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to  ProBuild and the fund&#039;s argument that the Jinkses had not paid for &amp;quot;the  improvement&amp;quot; because the contract amount was less than the dollar value of  the improvement, the Court of Appeals cited another section of the Michigan Construction Lien Act, which  &amp;quot;indicates that the total amount of liens cannot exceed the contract price  less payments made.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Accordingly, the appellate court rejected ProBuild and the fund&#039;s appeal, and affirmed the trial court&#039;s ruling in the Jinkses&#039; favor.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson is author of &amp;quot;The  Savvy Woman&#039;s Homebuying Handbook&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Trillion Dollar Women: Use  Your Power to Make Buying and Remodeling Decisions.&amp;quot; Ask her a real estate  question online or visit her Web site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rethinkrealestate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rethinkrealestate.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Law of the Land</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 10 10:59:29 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tara-Nicholle Nelson</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115454</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sizing up purchase deposits</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115291</link>
 <description>Different markets have different customs&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Dian Hymer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;In most states, it&#039;s customary, or required by law, for the  buyers to include a good faith deposit when they make an offer to purchase a  home. The deposit should not be given directly to the seller, but held by a  trustworthy third party that maintains a trust account specifically for home purchase  deposits, such as an escrow or title company, real estate firm or real estate  broker.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The deposit can be in the form of a check made out to the  third-party company or it can be wired into the appropriate account. The size of  the deposit you make is usually determined by market conditions and local  custom, except for specific types of sales, such as probate sales or sales of  homes in a housing development where a minimum deposit is required.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;HOUSE HUNTING TIP: Your deposit will become part of your  downpayment if the sale goes through. Depending on how your contract is  written, your deposit should be refundable if you are unable to satisfy a  contingency, after exercising due diligence to do so. Your contract should  include contingencies for inspections, satisfactory condition of title to the  property, your ability to line up financing and the lender&#039;s approval of an  appraisal of the property.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, if your inspections reveal defects that can&#039;t  be satisfactorily negotiated with the seller, your deposit should be returnable  if your contract provides for this. However, the deposit won&#039;t be released by  the holder to either the buyers or sellers without a release signed by both  parties indicating how to disperse the funds.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Be sure to check with a knowledgeable real estate attorney  to determine who is entitled to the deposit if you back out for a reason that&#039;s  not provided for in the contract. Real estate agents who aren&#039;t also attorneys  cannot advise you on this issue. If you end up in a dispute, the deposit holder  won&#039;t release the money to either party until the dispute is resolved. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;How large a good faith, or earnest money, deposit you make  will depend on several factors. In any case, your deposit should indicate your  intent to abide by the terms of the contract and close the sale. There is  usually no set amount required by law.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In California,  where home purchase contracts can include a liquidated damages clause, deposits  are often 3 percent of the purchase price. This clause puts a limit on damages  that could be awarded to the sellers if the buyers don&#039;t close the sale.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If buyers and sellers agree to include this clause in the  contract, state law limits the amount that can be awarded to the seller to 3  percent of the purchase price. In many areas of California, deposits tend to be 3 percent of  the offer price, even if the contract doesn&#039;t include a liquidated damages clause.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Like most elements of a purchase contract, the amount of the  deposit is negotiable. So, if you offer a $10,000 deposit on a $500,000 house,  the seller might counter your offer and ask for a deposit of $15,000, which is 3  percent of the purchase price.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The deposit can be made in two steps. You could offer $5,000  as an initial deposit, and increase that amount to a total of $15,000 upon  removal of contingencies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a hot seller&#039;s market, you might want to offer the full  amount up front, or make a larger deposit than you would if you weren&#039;t  potentially competing, to show your sincerity to the seller.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;THE CLOSING: If you&#039;re buying a short-sale listing that  might take two or three months for lender approval, you might want to keep the  deposit to a lower amount so that you don&#039;t tie up more money than necessary  for a long time period.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dian Hymer, a real  estate broker with more than 30 years&#039; experience, is a nationally syndicated  real estate columnist and author of &amp;quot;House Hunting: The Take-Along Workbook  for Home Buyers&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Starting Out, The Complete Home Buyer&#039;s  Guide.&amp;quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Dian Hymer&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Different markets have different customs</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Dian Hymer</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Dian Hymer&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115291</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mortgage payoff in a divorce</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115331</link>
 <description>Can split trigger due-on-sale clause?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Benny Kass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;DEAR BENNY: My wife  and I are in the process of getting a divorce. I am prepared to give her the  family home so that our children will not be disrupted any more than they  already are. I know that our mortgage lender will not relieve me of our joint  obligation to make the monthly payments, but hopefully that will not be a  financial problem for us. We have been advised that a lender can use the  &amp;quot;due on sale&amp;quot; clause in the mortgage documents to block this  transaction. Can this happen? --Tom&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;DEAR TOM: The short answer is no. Federal law permits  certain real estate transfers even though the loan documents contain the  &amp;quot;due on sale&amp;quot; clause.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let&#039;s look at this concept. Mortgage lenders are in the  business of making money, and obviously they do not like to allow people to  assume a low interest rate when rates are much higher. While this scenario sounds  unlikely in today&#039;s marketplace, many readers will recall the excessively high  mortgage interest rates during the past decade. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thus, many years ago, the mortgage industry came up with the  concept of &amp;quot;due on sale.&amp;quot; Most mortgage loan documents contain  language to the effect that if property that is secured by a mortgage is sold  or transferred without the lender&#039;s prior written consent, the lender has the  right to call the entire mortgage due, and insist on payment in full. This is  known as the &amp;quot;due on sale&amp;quot; clause.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There has been much litigation over this concept throughout  the country, and the great majority of the court cases have upheld the lender&#039;s  right to enforce the due-on-sale concept. In 1982, however, Congress enacted  the Garn-St. Germain Act (12 UCA 1701j-3), which imposed certain restrictions  on the enforcement of this clause.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This law contained nine specific exemptions where a lender  was not permitted to exercise its option pursuant to a due-on-sale clause. When  there is a real property loan secured by a lien on residential real property  containing fewer than five dwelling units -- including a lien on the stock of a  cooperative housing corporation or a residential manufactured home -- a lender  cannot enforce the due-on-sale clause under the following circumstances:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a transfer resulting from a decree of a dissolution of  marriage, legal separation agreement, or from an incidental property settlement  agreement, by which the spouse of the borrower becomes an owner of the  property;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a transfer where the spouse or children of the borrower become  an owner of the property;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a transfer to a relative resulting from the death of a  borrower;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a transfer by operation of law on the death of a joint  tenant or tenant by the entirety;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a transfer into an &amp;quot;inter vivos&amp;quot; trust in which  the borrower is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a  transfer of rights of occupancy in the property (i.e., the so-called &amp;quot;living  trust&amp;quot;);&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the creation of a purchase-money security interest for  household appliances (i.e., where you pledge your house in order to replace  your heating and air conditioning system);&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the granting of a leasehold interest of three years or  less not containing an option to purchase;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a subordinate lien that does not involve a transfer of  rights of occupancy in the property, and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;any other transfer or disposition described in regulations  prescribed by the Federal Home Loan Bank Board.  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;         &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I highlighted your situation by listing it first on the  list. Clearly, if you and your spouse enter into a formal, legal separation agreement,  or actually have a court order granting a divorce -- which contains language  reflecting the house transfer -- you are protected under the law and the lender  cannot exercise the due-on-sale clause, which I suspect is contained in your  mortgage documents,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, here are some suggestions before you proceed to  transfer the property to your wife:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First, before the divorce is finalized, arrange to transfer  the house. Normally, when real property is sold or transferred, there is a  transfer and recordation tax that has to be paid to the local jurisdiction. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For example, in the District    of Columbia, where I practice law, if the property is  appraised at more than $400,000, the local government will want to collect 2.9  percent of the appraised price. Normally, if you sell to a third party, each  side will split these costs, paying 1.45 percent. (If the property is worth  less than $400,000, the taxes are lowered to 1.1 percent each).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, if you are married and transfer the property to  your spouse, you do not have to pay either of these taxes. You pay only a  nominal fee to record the deed -- usually less than $30.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So discuss this with your attorney and arrange to transfer  the property before the divorce decree becomes final.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Second, what is your current mortgage interest rate? Rates  are quite low today, so you might want to consider refinancing first, so as to  take advantage of that lower rate. After that, you can have the property  transferred to your wife. You will, of course, have to explain your pending  divorce situation to the lender, but if you can qualify, there could be  substantial monthly savings.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally, I strongly recommend that you advise your lender of  your plans. Legally, it has no legal right to contest your decision, but it  always makes sense to keep lenders informed before you take any steps to change  the ownership.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;DEAR BENNY: My family  and I have lived in our current home for seven years. Do we qualify for the $6,500  tax credit for existing homeowners if we purchase a replacement principal  residence? If so, please tell me where to find in the Internal Revenue Service  regulations to file for it. --Don&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;DEAR DON: Last year, Congress expanded the tax credits  available to homebuyers. The new law allows existing homeowners to buy a new house  -- not to exceed $800,000 -- and so long as they owned and lived in their  current home for at least five consecutive years out of eight years prior to  the purchase date of the new home.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you qualify, you can claim a tax credit equal to 10  percent of the home&#039;s purchase price, up to a maximum of $6,500. However, there  are income limitations. If you are a single taxpayer, you cannot claim the  credit if your income is over $125,000; the limit for joint taxpayers is  $225,000.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One interesting fact of the new law is that you do not have  to sell your existing home; if you can afford to keep it as a rental, this does  not disqualify you from the tax credit. Also, the home does not have to cost  more than that value of your present residence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A tax credit is not the same as a tax deduction. The latter  allows you only to reduce the amount of the tax owed by the percent of your tax  bracket. A tax credit is a full dollar-for-dollar deduction of what you would  otherwise owe the IRS.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For more information, go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.federalhousingtaxcredit.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;federalhousingtaxcredit.com&lt;/a&gt; (sponsored by the National Association of Home Builders) or to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irs.gov&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IRS Web site&lt;/a&gt; and locate Form 5405.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;DEAR BENNY: Our home  equity lender has instituted a new flood insurance requirement. They now  require homeowners to carry coverage equal to either 80 percent of their hazard  insurance coverage amount or the unpaid principal balance of all liens on the  property, whichever is greater. If this amount is more than the maximum  $250,000 of coverage available through the National Flood Insurance Program, the  lender requires we carry the maximum $250,000. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;My question: In our  case, even the $250,000 coverage amount is much more than the unpaid liens on  the property, which total about $155,000. Can the lender legally require a  coverage amount greater than the total amount of unpaid liens? --Therese&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;DEAR THERESE: This is a common problem that homeowners face,  not only with their home equity loan but with their primary (first) mortgage as  well. I firmly believe that a lender can insist on insurance coverage only up  to the amount of the moneys owed to them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, that&#039;s my opinion; not everyone agrees with me,  especially mortgage lenders.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The answer to your question depends on the state law where  your property is located. It is my understanding that many states have enacted  legislation specifically prohibiting a lender from requiring insurance that  exceeds the amount of the mortgage loan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Talk with a local attorney about your situation. If there is  no law, complain to your lender and send a copy of your complaint to your state  attorney general. If enough people complain, the lenders may cave.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Benny L. Kass is a  practicing attorney in Washington, D.C., and Maryland. No legal relationship is created  by this column. Questions for this column can be submitted to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:benny@inman.com&quot;&gt;benny@inman.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Benny L. Kass&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Can split trigger due-on-sale clause?</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Benny Kass</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Benny L. Kass&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115331</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Feng shui staging tips</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115390</link>
 <description>Book Review: &#039;Sell Your Home Fast in a Buyer&#039;s Market&#039;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Book Review&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;   Title: &amp;quot;Sell Your Home Fast in a Buyer&#039;s Market:  Secrets from an Expert Green Feng Shui Staging Designer&amp;quot;&lt;br /&gt;   Author: Norma Lehmeier Hartie&lt;br /&gt;   Publisher: Lingham Press, 2010; 232 pages; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Sell-Your-Home-Buyers-Market/dp/0977963314/ref=sr_1_14?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;qid=1266420233&amp;amp;sr=1-14&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;$17.95  amazon.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In business, they say that when the market is bad or revenues  slow down, entrepreneurs should fight the urge to cut costs when it comes to  marketing -- in fact, upping the investment in marketing is one way businesses  find they can counteract slow markets.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This counterintuitive truism also applies with real estate.  While slow-market sellers generally want and need to pinch pennies, the  investment of time, money and effort in strategic home staging often pays off  in terms of getting your home sold -- period -- and certainly getting it off  the market in a shorter time frame than its non-staged competition.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The aim of Norma Lehmeier Hartie&#039;s new book, &amp;quot;Sell Your  Home Fast in a Buyer&#039;s Market: Secrets from an Expert Green Feng Shui Staging  Designer,&amp;quot; is to help home sellers use staging to best their homes&#039;  competition in a market where buyers have many more homes than normal from  which to choose. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In distinguishing this book from the many others on staging,  Hartie states that she &amp;quot;departs from traditional staging,&amp;quot; which &amp;quot;seems fake.&amp;quot; She explains that she will teach readers how to make buyers &amp;quot;want to  step into the lifestyle that you have created,&amp;quot; which intrigued (and  confused) me a bit, as it echoed what Hartie deemed the &amp;quot;fake&amp;quot;-ness  of traditional staging.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;But Hartie elaborates that her approach to staging is  designed to respond to the average buyer&#039;s basic senses of sight, sound and  smell -- plus the sixth sense of &amp;quot;how it feels,&amp;quot; which she addresses  using the energetic precepts of feng shui, the ancient Chinese science of  placement, aesthetics and energy, or qi (&amp;quot;chi&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hartie acknowledges up front that price is the No. 1 factor  that determines whether your home will sell, lest you think you could list your  home at an unjustifiably high price and get it sold fast, just because the feng  shui of the place is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She launches the book with two non-staging-specific  chapters on preparing to sell your home, including finding and interviewing  agents, creating an action plan, and photographing your home; and smart home  pricing -- including a caution against the common trap of overpricing. These  sections contain some useful sidebars and interesting insights from active real  estate brokers and agents on the home features and pricing considerations in  various regions around the country.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Then, as all good feng shui advisors do, Hartie moves into  chapters on decluttering and cleaning -- helping readers first understand what  clutter is (in the context of preparing a home for sale), why it&#039;s a problem, where  it should go and how to go about getting it there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When it comes to cleaning, Hartie&#039;s green tendencies begin  to show, as she provides recipes for non-toxic, non-chemical cleaning solutions  and a very detailed, step-by-step action plan for cleaning an entire home without  chemicals. This might sound basic, but cleaning standards are so personal  that it is very common for do-it-yourself sellers to inadvertently skip a step  (or 10) or miss an element of housecleaning without a thorough checklist to  guide them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After teaching you &amp;quot;green&amp;quot; cleaning techniques, Hartie pleads her case for going green, incorporating thoughts from practicing real  estate agents who have seen buyers&#039; increased focus on green housing features  like tankless water heaters and sustainable flooring materials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She then  explores the home improvements that have been shown to make a difference in  getting homes sold, also offering a checklist against which sellers can  evaluate their home&#039;s current toilets, front doors and the like to determine  whether they might be worth replacing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a section entitled, &amp;quot;Present a Memorable First Impression,&amp;quot;  Hartie interviews a landscaping expert to generate tips on creating curb appeal  and staging a home&#039;s outdoor areas. Then, she gives a primer on &amp;quot;negative  energies&amp;quot; and how to get rid of them, through smudging, incense and sacred  sound (e.g., cymbals, gongs, etc.). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hartie closes the book with a massive section called &amp;quot;How to  Make Your Home Look and Feel Great,&amp;quot; which includes thoughts on using feng shui&#039;s  rules and guidelines, creating positive energy and balance in a home, selecting  eco-friendly finish materials and design products, furniture  arrangement and various lists of &amp;quot;room-specific&amp;quot; staging tips.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In &amp;quot;Sell Your Home Fast in a Buyer&#039;s Market: Secrets  from an Expert Green Feng Shui Staging Designer,&amp;quot; sellers looking for a  very complete idea of the energetic or green steps they can take to clean and  otherwise prepare their homes for sale will find a useful tool.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson is author of &amp;quot;The  Savvy Woman&#039;s Homebuying Handbook&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Trillion Dollar Women: Use  Your Power to Make Buying and Remodeling Decisions.&amp;quot; Ask her a real estate  question online or visit her Web site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rethinkrealestate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rethinkrealestate.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Book Review: &#039;Sell Your Home Fast in a Buyer&#039;s Market&#039;</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 10 10:26:50 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tara-Nicholle Nelson</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115390</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A lender&#039;s end to overages</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115217</link>
 <description>Will new rules spur other banks to follow suit?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Jack Guttentag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bank of America recently delivered the following message to its loan  officers: &lt;i&gt;&amp;quot;Policy Change: Effective  with initial locks on or after Jan. 21, 2010, overages will not be allowed on  either purchase or refinance transactions.&amp;quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some years ago, I had occasion to compare the marketing of home  mortgages by lenders in the U.S.  with the marketing of carpets in Middle Eastern bazaars. The comparison favored  the carpet merchants, who didn&#039;t pretend their prices were fixed. Virtually all  carpet buyers know that in the bazaar, bargaining is the rule. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While  less-competent bargainers may pay a little more, they are paying for their  incompetence, not their innocence of the rules. In contrast, a large proportion  of mortgage borrowers did not understand that they were in a mortgage bazaar --  they paid for their innocence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The price of innocence is called an &amp;quot;overage.&amp;quot; It is the  difference between the price a lender posts with its loan officers -- which is  the price the lender expects to receive -- and the price the loan officer (LO)  charges the borrower.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the posted price is 5 percent and zero points, for  example, and the LO charges the borrower 5 percent and 0.5 point, the 0.5 point  is the overage. Typically, the LO will get half. Interested readers will find a  full discussion of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mtgprofessor.com/A%20-%20Shopping%20for%20a%20Mortgage/what_is_an_overage.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;how overages work&lt;/a&gt; on my Web site.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We have not always had overages. In the 1920s, before there were  secondary markets, consumers who wanted mortgages visited the offices of  commercial banks, savings banks, or savings and loan associations, and dealt  with salaried employees who had no discretion or incentive to adjust prices.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Overages arose following the development of secondary mortgage markets  after World War II. Secondary markets made it possible to go into the loan  origination business without becoming a regulated financial institution.  Because you could sell loans as fast as you made them, all you needed was a  little capital and a line of credit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These firms are &amp;quot;mortgage  companies,&amp;quot; or (as they much prefer) &amp;quot;mortgage banks.&amp;quot; I  sometimes refer to them as &amp;quot;temporary lenders&amp;quot; as distinguished from  &amp;quot;portfolio lenders&amp;quot; who hold the loans they originate in their  portfolios. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mortgage banking developed its own operating methods and a culture to  match that were very different from those of depository institutions. They  invested very little in physical facilities designed to attract walk-in traffic  during business hours. Instead, they retained loan officers (LOs) to actively  pursue clients, as opposed to sitting behind a desk waiting for clients to  appear.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To develop purchase-loan business, LOs courted real estate sales agents,  making themselves available to the agents wherever and whenever they were  needed to take a loan application, which might be on the hood of an automobile  on a Sunday morning. To develop refinance business, LOs might camp out in the  office of a public agency that maintains records of deeds and liens, developing  lists of borrowers who might profit from a refinance.  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Because LOs did most of their work out of the office, subject to little  supervision, they were compensated largely or entirely on a commission basis.  While legally employees of the mortgage bank, LOs operated largely as if they  were independent contractors. And the more loans they brought in, the more  independent they were.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Overages were part of the package. Most LOs wanted to be free to charge  what the traffic would bear, and profit from it. The lender who wouldn&#039;t  tolerate overages would lose LOs, and the most successful LOs would be the  first to leave.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The LO-based mortgage origination system made the depository office  obsolete as a source of mortgage loans. Depository institutions that wanted to  be major players in the home-loan market had to hire their own loan officers --  or acquire an entire mortgage banking firm as an affiliate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The affiliate  approach was the more popular because it avoided clash between very different  cultures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I recall my shock when I joined the board of a large savings and loan  association some years ago and found that the CEO was the third most highly  compensated employee of the association. The two who earned more were LOs who  had not yet been moved into a separate affiliate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The general attitude of most depository institutions has been that  overages were a necessary evil that they would like to eliminate, if they could  do it without losing their best loan producers. Bank of America has evidently  decided that that time had come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not the least of the reasons is that under  revisions to Truth in Lending recently proposed by the Federal Reserve, lenders  will not be able to share overages with LOs. This will eliminate the financial  incentive for LOs to charge overages. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My guess is that other major lenders will soon follow suit, if they  haven&#039;t done so already. I won&#039;t find out about it until one of their LOs  writes me, which is how I discovered the news about Bank of America. No lender  is going to put out a press release announcing that they will no longer  overcharge their customers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ending of the mortgage bazaar is not the beginning of the end for  LOs. They will remain the dominant mortgage delivery system, and while  borrowers will no longer be in a bazaar, they will be in a lottery in which  those with winning tickets work with an excellent LO and those with losing  tickets deal with clueless LOs. In a forthcoming article, I&#039;ll have some tips  about improving your odds in this lottery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The writer is  professor of finance emeritus at the Wharton  School of the University of Pennsylvania.  Comments and questions can be left at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mtgprofessor.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.mtgprofessor.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Jack Guttentag&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Will new rules spur other banks to follow suit?</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 10 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Jack Guttentag</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Jack Guttentag&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115217</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Buyers balk at markup on flips</title>
 <link>http://www.inman.com/inmaninf/storyxml/news/115298</link>
 <description>Mood of the Market&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class=&#039;&#039;&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#039;m not really sure exactly when investors got such a bad  name. Once upon a time, every other person I met wanted to be one. Maybe it was  the imprimatur of slick, infomercial-esque get-rich-quickness that kick-started  the national anti-real-estate-investor antipathy. It probably didn&#039;t help when  investors, only a small percentage of whom can accurately be called  &amp;quot;flippers,&amp;quot; ended up squarely on the wrong end of the foreclosure-crisis  finger-pointing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably wrongfully so, as the last numbers I could find --  from 2008 -- showed that only 20 percent of the foreclosures in America at the  time were on non-owner-occupied homes, which is disproportionately low,  considering that 33 percent of homes in America are owned by investors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All last year, during the deepest depths of the foreclosure  crisis, I saw buyer after buyer get outbid -- or underbid, but still bested --  by cash investors seeking to make the most of the decline in home values. While  I felt deeply for the homebuyers who lost out, I also saw how investors played  a big role in mopping up the excess inventory that was depressing values, and  could appreciate their role in the market&#039;s recovery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then, in January, the Department of Housing and Urban  Development lifted the FHA loan anti-flipping guideline, which had prevented  buyers from using an FHA-insured loan to buy a home that had been bought within  the previous 90 days. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now, my buyer clients and I are seeing the maturation of the  investor-buy-foreclosure phenomenon, as we see listing after listing that was  purchased at foreclosure auction, rehabbed/remodeled/upgraded/primped to within  an inch of its life, and put back on the market for resale, at an obvious -- and  sometimes steep -- markup.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At this point, I&#039;ve done this so many times I could script  it:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Scene: Buyers enter the house: &amp;quot;Wow -- this is  gorgeous. They did a ton of work. Oh my gosh -- look at those appliances. Is  that Wolf/Viking/Kenmore Elite (depending on price range)? Gorgeous. All new  bathrooms, too?! Distressed bamboo on the floors -- I love this. They made such  great choices. We basically wouldn&#039;t have to do a thing to move in!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Buyers leave the house -- &amp;quot;We&#039;d love to make an offer.  Will you run the comps for us and give us the background? Ta-ta! Talk to you  soon! So excited!!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I call the buyers -- &amp;quot;OK, well, I&#039;ve sent you the  comparables. This place is actually priced $10,000 below the nearest identical  comparable that sold a month ago, and of course that one wasn&#039;t  remodeled.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Buyers: &amp;quot;Fabulous -- it&#039;s totally worth that, at least.  Do you think we&#039;ll need to offer more than asking to beat out the other buyers?  We&#039;re OK with doing that -- we&#039;d go up to $20,000 over asking. Oh -- quick  question -- are the owners investors?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Yes.&amp;quot;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Buyers: &amp;quot;Can you find out what they paid for it?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Sure, I can research what they paid for it. Here  it is -- they bought it on the county courthouse steps for X, before doing the  work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Buyers: &amp;quot;They paid what?!? But that&#039;s $100,000 less  than the list price!! We want to offer $80,000 below asking. Write it up,  please.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As much as we give sellers a hard time for overpricing their  homes because they are confused about what truly determines the value of a home  (hint: it&#039;s not how much you need to buy your move-up home), buyers are equally  guilty, at times. The fact that a home was rehabilitated or is owned by an  investor does not inherently lower the value of that home -- especially when  the improvements made were quality improvements that truly added value to the  property. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Apparently, no buyer wants to feel like someone is profiting  off of them. However, the sudden plummeting in a buyer&#039;s sense of what a place  is worth belies the reality of even the flippiest of flippers&#039; investment in  the home. It&#039;s not always just a matter of slapping the cheapest paint on the  ugliest house. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Often, the investor paid out a large sum of cash or put down  a lot of money to get a loan to buy the home in the first place, at a sizeable  opportunity cost when you consider what else they could have been doing with  the cash. Then, they paid closing costs (anywhere from 2 percent to 5 percent  of the purchase price, or more), permit fees, city inspectors, carrying costs  (mortgage interest and property taxes) and advanced big, huge lump sums of cash  to do the very work that made the buyers ooh and ahh. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is, the seller  invested a large amount of cash that the buyer doesn&#039;t have and can&#039;t get, on  today&#039;s mortgage market, to upgrade the home, so that the buyer won&#039;t have to.  Oh, and the seller will pay all those fees again, plus the buyer agent&#039;s  commission, when the home is resold.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And what&#039;s more -- a home is simply worth what it&#039;s worth!  There&#039;s no room for sour grapes in real estate -- if someone else had the cash,  the risk tolerance and the wherewithal to buy a foreclosed home at auction and  rehabilitate it to a place where its value was much higher than what they paid,  why begrudge them their profit and yourself a great house in move-in condition  simply because you&#039;re mad? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If the work is shoddy or the value isn&#039;t truly there, that&#039;s  one thing. But to throw a tantrum and lose out on a great home because you  don&#039;t want someone else to profit? That&#039;s what I call cutting off your house  just to spite your face.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tara-Nicholle Nelson is author of &amp;quot;The  Savvy Woman&#039;s Homebuying Handbook&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Trillion Dollar Women: Use  Your Power to Make Buying and Remodeling Decisions.&amp;quot; Ask her a real estate  question online or visit her Web site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rethinkrealestate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.rethinkrealestate.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--BEGIN CONTACT--&gt; &lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;contactinfo&quot;&gt;What&#039;s your opinion? Leave your comments below or send a  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inman.com/opinion/letter-to-editor&quot;&gt;letter to the editor&lt;/a&gt;.  To contact the writer, click the byline at the top of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!--END CONTACT--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 <subtitle>Mood of the Market</subtitle>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 10 09:12:21 -0700</pubDate>
 <author>Tara-Nicholle Nelson</author>
 <copyright>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-type-text field-field-copyright&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item odd&quot;&gt;Copyright 2010 Tara-Nicholle Nelson&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</copyright>
 <credit>&lt;a href=&#039;http://www.inman.com&#039; target=&#039;_blank&#039;&gt;Inman News&lt;/a&gt;</credit>
 <category>Real Estate</category>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">inmannews115298</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
